In this video I would like to discuss with you
在本视频中 我们要学习
how to choose noise parameters and how to evaluate this choice.
如何选择噪音参数 以及如何评估选择
This is not only related to the unscented Kalman filter,
这不仅和无损卡尔曼滤波器相关
but it can be applied to any Bayesian filter.
同样适用于贝叶斯滤波器
When we talked about our process and our measurement models,
我们讨论过程和测量模型时
we introduced several sources of uncertainty.
介绍过几种不确定性的来源
In the process model, we introduced the process noise nu k.
在过程模型中 我们引入了过程噪音 vk
And in the measurement model,
在测量模型中
we introduced the measurement noise omega k.
我们引入了测量噪音 ωk
In case of a radar measurement, this was the noise of the distance measurement
在雷达测量中 这代表距离测量值噪音 ρ
rho, the angle measurement phi, and the radial velocity rho dot.
角测量值 φ 的噪音 以及径向速度 ρ 点的噪音
We also quantified the noise with the process noise covariance matrix and
我们还使用过程噪音协方差矩阵
the measurement noise covariance matrix.
和测量噪音协方差矩阵进行了噪音量化
So these are the variances of the noise.
这些是噪音的方差
And they quantify how strong the noise is.
它们表示噪音强度
But we haven't discussed where we get these values from.
但是 我们还不知道这些值是怎么来的
Let's start with the measurement noise.
我们从测量噪音开始
This noise describes how precise the sensor can measure.
测量噪音描述了传感器的测量精确度
It means we have to look into the sensor manual and
我们必须查看传感器手册
see how precise the sensor is.
查看其精确度
For example, we might read that radar can measure the distance rho
例如 手册里可能说明 雷达能了两的距离为 ρ
with the standard deviation of 0.3 meters.
标准偏差为 0.3 米
This means we know the value for the variance sigma rho squared,
因此 我们就得到了σρ 的平方
which is 0.09 meters squared.
0.09 平方米
We also have to assume the noise is white and normally distributed.
我们还必须假设它是白噪音 正态分布
Which is of course not true for some sensors.
当然 对有些传感器 这种假设是错的
It is a little more difficult to choose an appropriate process noise.
选择过程噪音要更难一些
In reality,
在现实中
objects in a traffic environment don't move with white acceleration noise.
交通环境里的对象移动时加速噪音不是白噪音
This would mean a driver constantly switches between gas and brake.
也就是说 司机会不断踩油门和刹车
So we really apply a strong approximation here,
因此 我们在这里使用强近似
by assuming a white process noise.
假设过程噪音为白噪音
A rule of thumb for getting useful values is the following.
要得到有用的值 一定要谨记下面的规则
Try to estimate what the maximum acceleration is you
尽量估算你在环境中可能碰到的
expect in your environment.
最大加速度
Let's say we want to track cars in an urban environment.
比如 我们想追踪城市环境中的汽车
Then these cars usually don't accelerate or
这些车加速或刹车
brake stronger than 6 meters per second squared.
的加速度通常不会超过 6 米每平方秒
Now, the rule of thumb says,
现在 一定要记住
choose half of the maximum acceleration you expect as process noise.
选择预期最大加速度的一半作为过程噪音
In this case, we would choose 9 meters squared over seconds to the power 4 as
在本例中 我们选择 9 平方米每 s 的四次方
variance for the acceleration noise.
作为加速噪音的方差
If this is a good value for you really depends on your application.
这个值到底好不好 取决于你的应用
Is it important for your application to react fast on changes?
应用对变更的反应很快是不是很重要？
Then you choose the process noise a little higher.
如果是 那你要选择更高一点的过程噪音
Is it important to provide smooth estimations?
提供平滑个估算是不是很重要？
Then you choose the process noise a little lower.
如果是 那你要选择更低一点的过程噪音
Usually, you want to know of course if you set up the noise parameters
当然 你通常都需要知道噪音参数设置
correctly.
是否正确
For that purpose, you can run a consistency check on the filter.
为此 你可以运行滤波器一致性检查
What does consistency mean?
一致性是什么意思呢？
At every time cycle, we calculate the measurement prediction zk + 1 pipe k and
在每个时间循环里 我们计算每次预测的测量预测值 zk+1|k
the covariance matrix S of this prediction.
以及协方差矩阵 S
Then we receive the actual measurement zk + 1 for that time step.
然后 我们收到该时间步的实际测量值 zk+1
In this example, everything looks okay.
在本例中 看起来一切正常
The actual measurement occurred somewhere inside the error ellipse.
实际测量值在误差椭圆内部
But this might look differently.
但实际情况中 看起来可能不一样
Imagine you set up a filter, and your measurement looks like this.
假设你设置了一个滤波器 你的测量是这样的
Here, something is wrong.
这里出了问题
You constantly underestimate the uncertainty of
你每次都低估了预测测量值
the predicted measurement.
的不确定性
This means your filter is not consistent.
这说明你的滤波器是不一致的
Of course, these are all stochastic processes.
当然 这些都是随机过程
And it might just be a natural coincidence.
也可能是自然巧合
But if the results keep looking like this,
但如果结果一直都这样
this explanation is extremely unlikely.
那这个解释就过于牵强了
This result tells you that you underestimate the uncertainty
结果告诉你 你的系统低估了
in your system.
不确定性
Your estimate is less precise than you think.
估算的精确度比你想的要低
The same can happen in the other direction.
在另一个方向 也可能发生同样的情况
Look at this example.
看这个例子
Here you overestimate the uncertainty of your system.
这里 你高估了系统的不确定性
It means your estimate is actually more precise than you think.
也就是说 估算的精确度比你想的要高
So this filter is also inconsistent.
因此 滤波器也不一致
A filter is consistent if it provides a realistic estimation uncertainty.
滤波器一致是指 能提供真实的估算不确定性
It is very easy to check the consistency of your filter, and
滤波器一致性检查很简单
I recommend to always do that when you design a filter.
建议你在设计滤波器是 始终检查一致性
An important consistency check is called NIS,
有种重要的一致性检查 叫做 NIS
it means Normalized Innovation Squared.
全称是归一化新息平方
This is how the NIS is calculated.
这是 NIS 的计算方式
Its meaning is very intuitive.
它很直观
The innovation is the difference between the predicted measurement and
新息是预测测量值和
the actual measurement.
实际测量值之间的差
And normalized means you put it into relation to the covariance matrix S.
归一化是指相对于矩阵 S 的协方差而言
That's why you have the inverse of the matrix S here.
因此 我们这里有矩阵 S 的逆
The NIS is just a scalar number and super easy to calculate.
NIS 只是一个标量数字 计算超级简单
But you need to know what number to expect.
但你要对数字有合理预期
For that, you need to know something about the statistics of this NIS.
为此 你需要了解 NIS 的一些统计知识
The NIS value follows a distribution which is called chi-squared
NIS 的值分布符合
distribution.
卡方分布
If you Google chi-squared distribution, you will find a table like this.
如果你谷歌搜索卡方分布 你会找到这样的一个表格
And this table tells you the number you should expect for your NIS.
里面是 NIS 可能得到的数字结果
Let's find the right number for our example.
我们找到本例中的正确数字
DF means degrees of freedom.
DF 表示自由度
That's the dimension of our measurement space.
这是测量空间的维度
We have a three-dimensional radar measurement.
我们有一个三维的雷达测量值
So we have three degrees of freedom.
因此 我们有三个自由维度
So what do all these numbers mean?
那这些数字都代表什么呢？
0.95 says statistically, in 95% of all cases,
0.95 代表 在统计意义上 所有情况下 有 95% 的概率
your NIS will be higher than 0.352.
你的 NIS 会超过 0.352
And this column says in 5% of all cases your NIS will be higher than 7.815.
这一栏说 在所有情况下 有 5% 的概率 你的 NIS 会超过 7.815
Let's remember this number, 7.8.
我们记住这个数字 7.8
What you can always do when you design a filter is plot the 95% line.
设计滤波器时 一定要画出 95% 这条线
In our case, that's 7.8.
在本例中 它的值是 7.8
And then for every time step k, calculate and plot also the NIS value.
然后 对每个时间步 k 计算并画出 NIS 值
If you see something like this, then everything looks great.
如果你得到这样一张图 则一切很正常
Sometimes you are over the 95% line, but that's what we expect.
有时候会超过 95% 的线 但这和我们预期的一样
If you see something like this, it means you underestimate the uncertainty in
如果你得到这样一张图 这说明系统低估了
your system, like in the example we saw before.
不确定性 就像我们之前看过的例子一样
If you see something like this,
如果你得到这样一张图
it means you overestimate the uncertainty in your system.
说明你高估了系统的不确定性
Your estimations are actually more precise than you think.
你的估算的精确度比你想的要高
Unfortunately, the NIS test does not tell you where the mistake comes from,
不幸的是 NIS 练习不会告诉你错误原因
but it gives you at least some feedback.
但至少它提供了一些反馈信息
In this case, for example, it might be a good idea to reduce the process noise
例如 在本例中 你可以尝试降低过程噪音
a little bit and try again.
然后再试试
In the project, at the end of this lesson, take a look at your NIS and
在本课末尾的实战项目里 你需要检查你的 NIS
use it to check your process noise settings.
并利用它检查你的过程噪音设置